Now let's see how well this works when
we have something like a branch that is
just always taken. In that case the
entry for that branch will just be all
ones in the history. That branch has a
fixed PC. It always has the same
history. When we extore them we will be
using only one two bit counter. So
pretty much although we have a long
history if the branch is just a
repetition of the same thing we are
ending up using only one of the two bit
counters. So the additional cost
relative to just having an array of two
bit counters is that now we're keeping
an 11 bit history for this branch. So
still the cost is not just two bits.
It's really let's say 11 or 16 bits plus
two. But it's much less than a long
history plus 2 to the n times a two bit
counter. If we have a branch that is
never taken, we can do the same
reasoning and end up using a single
counter. If we have a branch that has
something like NT NT, it really has only
two possible histories 0 1 0 1 0 1 etc.
or 1 0 1 0 1 0 etc. So it ends up using
two counters. So if we have a lot of
these counters as you can see most
branches are going to be like these. We
will be using very very few entries by
these branches which leaves us plenty of
counters for branches where we have a
very long pattern where we will be using
something like you know 16 histories and
thus use something like 16 counters. As
you can see in this organization pretty
much the branches that need more
counters get them. The branches that
need relatively few counters get them.
The only really additional cost relative
to just having the counters is the
histories. The downside is that again
some branches with particular histories
might overlap in which counter they use
with other branches and other histories.
Pretty much my branch exord with its
history might map to the same counter as
some other branch and its own history
when they are exort. But this happens
very rarely if the BHT is large. And now
it can be large because each entry is
just two bits.